<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine considerations touching the present factions in the Kings dominions.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1697</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E466_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205217</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864647</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864647</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116879</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78467)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116879)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 74:E466[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine considerations touching the present factions in the Kings dominions.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber [i.e. October] 6".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116879:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>CERTAINE</hi> CONSIDERATIONS <hi>TOUCHING</hi> THE PRESENT FACTIONS IN The <hi>KINGS</hi> Dominions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed in the Year, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116879:2"/>
            <head>Certaine Conſiderations touching the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Factions in the <hi>KING'S DOMINIONS.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Dominions belonging to the Crown of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> are divided into three Kingdomes. Every Kingdome is divided into three <hi>Factions:</hi> 1. <hi>Royaliſts.</hi> 2. <hi>Preſbyterians.</hi> 3. <hi>Independents.</hi> I rank them according to ſeniority, not forme: for every one knowes that <hi>Loyaltie</hi> was before <hi>Presbyterie</hi> in time, and <hi>Presbyterie</hi> before <hi>Independencie:</hi> though now, according to the good pleaſure of God, the laſt is become firſt, and the firſt laſt.</p>
            <div type="kingdom">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of</hi> ENGLAND.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ENgland</hi> is divided into 1. <hi>Independents.</hi> 2. <hi>Presbyterians.</hi> 3. <hi>Royaliſts.</hi> The <hi>Independents,</hi> make the <hi>Army,</hi> the <hi>Committee of Safety</hi> at <hi>Derbyhouſe,</hi> the <hi>Committees in the Countries,</hi> have all the <hi>Garriſons</hi> and <hi>Caſtles</hi> in the Kingdome in their hands; and are a great part of the <hi>Houſe of Commons:</hi> who being counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced with power without, doe by their unity, aſſiduity, and reſolution within, either intimidate or inſidiate the judgements and affections of other men; and ſo carry on all their deſignes with the forme of Supreme Authority: Which was firſt wreſted from the KING by the <hi>Preſbyterians,</hi> and now cheated and wreſted from them by the <hi>Independents;</hi> who like cunning Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116879:3"/>of their Art open not all the boxes of their Principles at once.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> make a great part in the Houſe of Lords cleerly: And ſo they doe in the Houſe of Commons (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding many of them have turned <hi>Renegado's,</hi> and gone over to the <hi>Independents</hi>) when they dare meet, and ſtick to one another: which is accidentall, they being diſ-united by fear, intereſt, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>correſpondency, indifference of affection, and inſtability of judgement. For I eſteeme all the remnant of <hi>Royaliſts</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in the Houſe of Commons when the KING went away, to be of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> perſwaſion, as it is moſt favourable to Monarchy: though, as I ſaid, for the cauſes before, they give way to the <hi>Independents</hi> by their abſence, or ſervility of nature; as at firſt they did to the <hi>Presbyterians.</hi> How the reſt of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome are affected this way, appears firſt in the City of <hi>London:</hi> Where, without queſtion, much the ſupernumerary part are <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and are awed only by the activity of the <hi>Independent</hi> Faction; who working by Authority of Parliament, with whom they correſpond daily, are made to ſerve them, though not to love them. The reſt of the Kingdom are generally <hi>Presbyterian;</hi> not ſo much, I ſuppoſe, becauſe their names are upon the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Roll, (which however ought to be regarded) as becauſe they find the oppreſſion of Warre, and a headleſſe Government: And that Monarchy is more favoured by the Covenant; which they remember to have been leſſe grievous, and not ſo perpetuall, as the Government on foot is like to prove: For Kings may die, or their humours change. As for the Townes and Corporations, many of them have neſts of <hi>Sectaries,</hi> yet they are not all <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents:</hi> though they all hope for Liberty from them; and ſo by fighting with them againſt all others, they ſuppoſe they fight for themſelves. But from theſe, there is no fear of great dangers, were one Army of them broken; for they are not a conſiderable part of the Inhabitants; and all that can runne to defend the common Cauſe (as they call it) in the <hi>Armies;</hi> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no propagation of their Sect, but what is between man and wife, which muſt have ſome years to grow up. For it may be confidently averred, there hath been no conſiderable encreaſe of theſe parties, ever ſince they had power to perſwade and terrifie;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116879:3"/>both which they have done: which ſhewes they are no growing Faction, and being at their height, are endangered by one conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable check. For fear will then drive many off, whom intereſt or affection now makes to adhere; and confidence and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage reſtrain others, whom force at preſent hath enſlaved to their deſignes.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Royaliſts</hi> make a diſtreſſed company of Noble-men, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and others, who having engaged their Eſtates and Credits to compound with the Parliament, are all retired to a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate life, to eat the bread of carefulneſſe; expecting Gods good houre for their reſtauration: who are beaten out of all their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, but that of a good Conſcience, which remaines impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. Theſe, it did import the <hi>Parliament,</hi> whoſe power could not compel the judgement and reaſon, to have allured by ſoft and amicable entreaties, to a good aſſurance of peace and quietneſſe; which after the rough and deſtructive variations of an unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Warre, might perhaps have made impreſſion. But the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary being put in practice, and proceeding from thoſe whoſe principles have cried up Liberty of Conſcience, and Chriſtian Charity ſo much, and yet in their actions are the moſt ſanguinary and inflexible perſons in the world; it begat only an indignation againſt the hypocriſie of proud Conquerors; and left them fitted with vindicative reſolutions, to engage with the next party ſhould appear; which hath cauſed the late emergent troubles, and may cauſe more, upon the like probable overtures, if God prevent it not.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="kingdom">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of</hi> SCOTLAND.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SCotland</hi> is divided into 1. <hi>Presbyterians.</hi> 2. <hi>Royaliſts.</hi> 3. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents;</hi> not purely and properly ſo, but corruptly, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on deſigne.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> make up all the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the <hi>Army,</hi> the <hi>Committee of Eſtates</hi> at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> and all the <hi>whole Kingdome:</hi> who are thereto engaged by the Covenant, univerſally taken there; and as really adhered to <hi>in terminis;</hi> except by ſome late diſcontents, who would advance their humours and paſſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove it, and contrary to it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:116879:4"/>
The <hi>Royalists</hi> are made up of thoſe who were ſo before the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> and ſuch as were ſo by vertue of the <hi>Covenant.</hi> Of the later fort I may call all <hi>Scotland,</hi> now, but <hi>Argyles</hi> faction. For tis by obligation of the <hi>Covenant</hi> they come now to fight for the King againſt the Parliament, as by the ſame obligation they came before to fight for the Parliament againſt the King: The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence onely is, that then they broke it, and now they keep it: though God ſeemes to puniſh them now, for breaking of it then. But the <hi>Royall</hi> part I meane, are ſuch, of whom the famous <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of Montroſſe</hi> was Head, and by whoſe courage he was the ſcourge of all <hi>Scotland,</hi> when they were aſſiſting their falſe bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in <hi>England;</hi> And ſuch others, as now are incorporated, without doubt, into that number, who have reſolved to reſcue their King from baſe impriſonment. There wants onely the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of that incomparable and gallant Perſon, the <hi>Marqueſſe of Montroſſe,</hi> and then the undertaking is compleat: For it were a ſtrange improvidence, to let ſo much honour and virtue, as is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentally knowne to be in that <hi>Marqueſſe,</hi> fall to the ground: who being both a <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> and a <hi>Royaliſt,</hi> is the onely fit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to correct the turbulencie of <hi>Argyle,</hi> &amp; infelicity of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton,</hi> and perhaps not over-much integrity of <hi>Both.</hi> I write not this partially, or as a ſuborn'd perſon; for, God knowes, I am equally unknowne to them all.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Independents,</hi> as I ſaid, are ſuch as are ſo, not becauſe they have not taken the <hi>Covenant,</hi> but upon perſonall and private re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects: and it may be too, from an habituall inclination, made up of pride and envy, to croſſe any action may end with honour and happineſſe, to the maligned undertakers. Theſe conſiſt of <hi>Argyle,</hi> and his partie; who being a coward, is diſpoſed to the more miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe; for nothing is ſo much to be feared, as a coward not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together deprived of power. Tis not the principles of <hi>Cromwell,</hi> &amp;c. but his hatred to <hi>Hamilton,</hi> makes him correſpond with the <hi>Independents</hi> in <hi>England.</hi> His Nature is more to be ſuſpected then his Reaſon: and though that be not ſo great, but that many men are wiſer; yet his qualities are ſo bad, that few men are worſe. And without goodneſſe of nature, and a gracious improvement thereof, what are riches, wit, underſtanding, honour, and power, but ſo many fignall abilities to doe evill?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="kingdom">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:116879:4"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of</hi> IRELAND.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IReland</hi> is divided into 1. <hi>Papiſts.</hi> 2. <hi>Presbyterians.</hi> 3. <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Papiſts</hi> make the greater power in that Kingdome: which I ſuppoſe is granted by all. And tis almoſt incredible there ſhould be any power there but theirs: conſidering the ſeaſon they have had to doe any buſineſſe that concern'd them. How they are now diſabled, and made informidable, by their owne diviſions, the catching diſeaſe at this time of the whole world, moſt men know.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> conſiſt of the Lord <hi>Inchequin,</hi> and his Forces in <hi>Munſter:</hi> to whom if you adde his confederates, they muſt be rather conſidered as <hi>Royaliſts</hi> then <hi>Presbyterians.</hi> To whom alſo muſt be joyned all the <hi>Scots</hi> Forces in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter;</hi> with other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed well-wiſhers, who live in a Country, where tis victory enough to defend that little is remaining from the uſurpation of a common enemy.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Independents</hi> have their head-quarter at <hi>Dublin;</hi> where Col: <hi>Iones</hi> hath the whole Military Force: Being a qualified Emiſſarie from the Faction in <hi>England</hi> to ſecure that City: though his power tend rather to preſerve then augment. So that the Fate of this Kingdome in matters of Religion and Gods Worſhip, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on the maſtery of one of the other two.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Parliaments">
               <head>Of the two Parliaments of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England</hi> taken vulgarly, is onely the Houſe of Commons; for in that notion doe the common people generally receive it: becauſe when they ſpeak of a <hi>Parliament man</hi> or a <hi>Member</hi> of the Houſe, it agrees only with that Houſe. Though it may be taken really too; for who knowes not, how the Faction in that Houſe hath impoſed for theſe laſt years, upon the King and the Lords, with this difference only, that the King went away becauſe He was not able to endure it, but the Lords ſtayed, and did. But here is the great riddle of all, (ſay they in their own defence;) How a Faction, a prevailing Party, a minor
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116879:5"/>part can over-rule the greater? To this I can quickly Anſwer: 'Tis caſie for a few knaves to cozen a great many honeſt men. Was not the Pope, and a few Cardinalls, by this means too hard for all the world in the Councell of <hi>Trent?</hi> The Artifice of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning, which is the ſtudy of ſuſpicious natures, is too often known to have the better of innocency and right. But yet thoſe ends only God will bleſſe, which are wrought out upon the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid principles of integrity and vertue. How the firſt Faction hath proſpered, that ſaid a <hi>Minor</hi> part could not over-rule the <hi>Major;</hi> let them now ſpeak, that being become a Major of their own contriving, are now over-aw'd and terrified by a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. For ſo I eſteeme the <hi>Independent</hi> party within the Houſe to be; as all men know their Army without alſo, is a <hi>Minor</hi> part of the Kingdome: and yet becauſe they Act by unity and deſigne, are able to give Lawes to all others, who live at large, out of the ſtrength of confederacy and compact.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> is wholly <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> and would be Loyall if the Clergy would ſuffer them. They have now the third time ſent an Army into <hi>England.</hi> The firſt was for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. The ſecond for the Parliament here. And the third for the KING. Their firſt expedition was with Honour and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe; Their ſecond with Succeſſe and Profit; Their third, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Succeſſe, Honour, nor Profit. Yet I doe not take the reaſon to be in the fulminations of the Clergy, nor want of ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the undertakers; but of reſolution, good conduct and diſcipline in the Generall: who ought to have had exact care that Deeds and Declarations had been Uniforme. For the <hi>Scots</hi> at this time (above any other) had need to ſweeten their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into <hi>England</hi> with actions, as well as words: being their own friends are now againſt them, and the reſt of the people never yet were for them. The enmity of ſo many Ages, is not ſwallowed up with a few Years; nor their Ancient invaſions skinned over with other words of a Declaration, Engagement for Religion or Union of the Kingdome. For ſo long as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>predations of the Souldier upon the Countries accompanies the undertaking, as is uſed in all hoſtile invaſions, it will be eſteemed no better by the ſufferers; eſpecially if the <hi>Parliament</hi> vote it ſo. And let what will be told them, the people will never be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into the patience of being undone.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116879:5"/>But the great Queſtion now on foot is, who breakes the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> the <hi>Treaties,</hi> the <hi>Brother-hood</hi> of both Nations? The <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents</hi> charge the <hi>Scots</hi> with it, and the <hi>Scots</hi> them. In what particulars the <hi>Scots</hi> charge the <hi>Independents,</hi> is made publick and needs no repetition. But wherein the <hi>Independents</hi> charge the <hi>Scots</hi> is yet to doe. And yet (perhaps) in point of fact, it is not hard for either ſide to ſay ſomething: there having been for two years laſt paſt and more, a jealouſie raiſed between them, which muſt of neceſſity have brought forth ſome traverſes of diſtemper and diſcontent. But not to derive from matter of fact the inſincerity of either part, I ſhall fetch the Errours of the <hi>Independents</hi> from a higher fountaine, and lay down this poſition, That all the tranſactions of the <hi>Independents</hi> with the <hi>Scots,</hi> in their own deſperate neceſſities and hazards, were laid in fraud, treachery, ſelf-intereſt, and deep diſſimulation from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and it plainly now appeares, that they never meant to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Fraternity of the <hi>Scots,</hi> no longer then the Fraternity of the <hi>Scots</hi> ſhould be neceſſary to uphold them. For when the King, and His Party were all ſubdued, and no imaginable force likely to trouble them in the Kingdome; they preſently fell to expoſtulating with the <hi>Scots</hi> about their departure, and were drawing down all their Armies into the <hi>North,</hi> to be ready to force them out, in caſe they ſhould be remiſſe: after they had (not long ſince) with Prayers and Teares brought them in. Of which action, and many others, their conſciences and underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings accuſing them; and how much they had diſobliged their late confederate friends and brethren, it was not poſſible they ſhould conſent to ſuch an imprudent act of disbanding; when they knew, if they did, <hi>Preſbytery</hi> would preſently be ſetled; or if it were not, the <hi>Scots</hi> would be ready to ſee it done by power. Now theſe people, who cordially and candidly never entred into, nor ſince adhered to a reall fraternall union and intereſt with the <hi>Scots;</hi> yet pretended nothing leſſe, and at this time are become the moſt ungratefull Enemies both of <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>Covenanters,</hi> will I ſuppoſe by all the world, be eſteemed the true Fomenters and Authors of this ſecond War, which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, conſcious of their own provocations and hypocriſie, did look for, and expect with Armes in their hands. For it is not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116879:6"/>the firſt act of force, but of injuſtice, fraud, or diſhoneſty, that legitimates the commencement of a Nationall Warre: being a Tryall wherein God himſelf is made the Judge: And will in the end, I doubt, though for the preſent through his ſecret appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the face of things looke otherwiſe, have worſer effects in this Nation then we now think of: which God divert.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="synods">
               <head>Of the two Synods of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>England</hi> I take to be a company of men, ſet apart by the Houſe of Commons, to make all Divinity give obedience to the reſolutions of Parliament; and to conſult of nothing but <hi>proponente Senatu;</hi> as in the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> the Pope got the reines of that Councell into his hand, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing all things to be treated, <hi>proponentibus Legatis.</hi> What they have been about theſe many yeares is kept ſecret: but when the buſineſſe of the Treaty came into diſcourſe, they quickly reſolved, all of them but four, to be againſt it. And the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons made it one of their reaſons, for offering the three Bils be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Treaty; becauſe (otherwiſe) ſuch godly Divines, who are placed by the Parliament, ſhall be put out, and ſcandalous Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters reſtored to their places. By this, we know what Trade they are of, and how they get their living. But in the mean while they are but <hi>viatores;</hi> having not arrived to their end of power, nor it may be to their end of profit.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> otherwiſe by a more majeſticall name, called the <hi>Generall Aſſembly,</hi> are <hi>Comprehenſores:</hi> being arrived to the very <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Preſbytery;</hi> and ſomething too high for the Civill State. They enjoy by a ſtrange ſurreptitious uſurpation, a power equall to the Pope, and exerciſed only by more perſons. They indict themſelves, take cognizance of the Orders in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Committes of Eſtates: admoniſh and cenſure the Magiſtrate: And indeed do every thing but what they ſhould do, <hi>Preach the Goſpell of Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Both <hi>Synods</hi> agree to diſturb the Peace of both Kingdomes, and blow the people into Rebellions and Tumults; for which they are notable Inſtruments. Which the Parliament well knew, when they ſet their <hi>Synod</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> to write a Letter to the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116879:6"/>
                  <hi>Generall Aſſembly</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> that they might thereby lay an ambuſh at the back of the <hi>Scots</hi> Armies which were entred into <hi>England.</hi> But whether either of theſe <hi>Synods</hi> would ever agree, except in this one thing of troubling the Kingdomes, if they might be ſuffered to confer Notes, is a great queſtion: though at this preſent, upon concurring principles of worldly power and profit, they care not how they engage all the world beſide in the higheſt guilt, and extreameſt miſeries. Therefore, though there was not much Religion, yet theſe was not much imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency in his ſpeech, that ſaid, There was no way to end the diviſions in <hi>England;</hi> but to forbid all Preaching for one whole year.</p>
               <p>For I may, with the ſighes and groanes of a Chriſtian heart ſpeak it; That let us look back upon all Ages ſince Chriſtianity began to enlarge it ſelf upon the world, and we ſhall finde, that moſt of the Warres therein, have been raiſed by the profeſſors of it; and are owing to thoſe that call themſelves the Clergy and Miniſters of Chriſt, which agrees with his own propheſie in <hi>Mat.</hi> 30.34. diſcourſing upon the Commiſſion he had then gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven his Apoſtles. <hi>I came not</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>to ſend Peace on earth, but a Sword.</hi> And is verified from the perverſneſſe and inſtability of our natures, not in the quality of his moſt holy and peaceable Goſpell.</p>
               <p>What a tragicall <hi>audit</hi> would it be, to hear ſumm'd up all the lives of thoſe Chriſtian people that periſhed in the zealous Wars of the <hi>Holy Land?</hi> and yet that holy Father, the Pope, had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of his owne in the buſineſſe; the reducing of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Church into his ſubjection, with the three Patriarchs of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Antioch,</hi> and <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and making the <hi>Eaſterne</hi> Church a Chappell of eaſe to the <hi>Weſterne</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> and beſides Spirituall juriſdiction, had an eye alſo on Temporall profits: for while the Emperour was doing his errand, and waging War in the <hi>Holy Land,</hi> he encroached on the Emperours Temporalties in <hi>Italy.</hi> Neither were the reſt of the holy Clergie idle; for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindled in others the fire of Zeale, they preſently fell to warme themſelves at it, and to buy the Eſtates of ſuch Noblemen and others, as ſold them to ſet themſelves forward into the <hi>Holy Land. Godfrey</hi> ſold the Dukedome of <hi>Bovillon</hi> to the Biſhop of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116879:7"/>
                  <hi>Leige,</hi> and the Caſtle of <hi>Sartonſi</hi> and <hi>Monſa</hi> to the Biſhop of <hi>Vendune.</hi> And when the ſucceſſe of the Chriſtian Armes had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and Patriarchs were ſet up, they fell preſently to claiming of the Cities and Lands, and terrifying the Princes with Sacriledge; ſaying, thoſe voyages were undertaken not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for reſtoring the Churches Liberties, but her Lands. After theſe things, the Popes found out other arts, to divert the Cruſa do's for the Holy Land upon Chriſtians themſelves: as upon <hi>Greece;</hi> and againſt the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> upon the ſame Indulgences and Pardons, he did thoſe to the Holy Land. And this alſo he called the <hi>holy War,</hi> the war of <hi>Crucifix,</hi> the <hi>Army</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi> What other wars, enmities, and civill diſcords have been ſtirred up in ſeverall Nations by the inſtigation of the Church of Rome, to ſupport her ambition or avarice, let Hiſtories declare at large. How <hi>they</hi> have agreed ſince among themſelves, that broke away from the Church of Rome, becauſe they could not agree with her, I could wiſh were blotted out of the Hiſtories of latter Ages. We ſee Obedience to Princes is no better taught then it was before. All Kingdomes are ſet on fire by the ſame Principles, and differ only in the delivery, by other Perſons. The Doctors of <hi>Rome, Wittenberg, Geneva, Euric,</hi> can ſit in their Studies, if the good Spirit of God prevent them not, and Slay more men then ever <hi>Alexander</hi> or <hi>Ceſar</hi> did. And if any one ſhould ask me, why Prayers and Teares were thought in the primitive times, the Armes of the Church, and only lawfull Weapons againſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing Princes, enemies to God and Chriſt, and now Piſtols and Swords, when we live under Chriſtian Kings and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours? I can only ſay, that this is a ſecret wrapt up in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet of the Divine Councell, whereby God hath appointed for the diſciplining of the world, that one Age ſhould bring forth good fruit, and another evill.</p>
               <p>But when theſe things will have a remedy, if any enquire, it may as ſoone be anſwered, when the Magiſtrate ſhall be inveſted with what properly belongs to him, the <hi>Right of Dominion;</hi> Chriſt would not have his Diſciples as Lords, if Kings would not have them ſo neither; what do they but will the ſame things our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt willed before? There is no Argument to be uſed againſt them, no more then there can be againſt Scripture; &amp; yet
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116879:7"/>as much labour hath been taken to expound the one, and oppoſe the other, as in any two things in the world.</p>
               <p>In a word, we are come to that paſſe, that to lay a foundation of a durable Government, and provide for the peoples Safety, nothing is more neceſſary, then to take away the <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>Clergie,</hi> and their <hi>liberty</hi> of <hi>prevaricating</hi> in the <hi>Pulpits:</hi> for by this meanes we ſhall prevent as much as in us lies, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy judgements of God upon us, <hi>then which none are greater, no not plague, famine, or the ſword, then when he ſuffers a lying ſpirit to fill the mouthes of the Prophets:</hi> which were the words of Sir <hi>Robert Spotſwood</hi> at his death.</p>
               <p>And ſince every one can reforme another better then himſelf, 'tis fitteſt for the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> to reforme the <hi>Clergie,</hi> [eſpecially now we live in an Age, when the Laity and Secular men in morall vertue, Learning, and Piety, not only equall, but exceed them;] that they being the beſt of men, may mend others by their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as well as precept.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>Of the whole Controverſie between <hi>KING</hi> and <hi>PARLIAMENT</hi> in a brief Concluſion.</head>
               <p>TO conclude, It hath appeared to me, in the generall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of the times; that the queſtion never was amongſt any men, whether obedience ſhould be given to the ſupreme Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate? but, who that Supreme Magiſtrate was? or where it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſided? As if we could not tell, after ſo many Ages, and Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Kings and Princes, what the forme of our Government yet was; and that all this while, we ſhould (as it were) be Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by chance. But where the reaſon of all this is, and how the matter comes to be ventilated with no other ſucceſſe then the increaſe of animoſities and heats among men, muſt be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to Gods Judgements on the Nation. For it is certaine, that all truths whatſoever, receive not their <hi>Quietus eſt</hi> from any Arguments of men, or power of reaſon alone, without a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current temper in the affections which God gives to imbrace them. It could not otherwiſe be, that what hath been received for ſo many Ages for an univerſall truth, by wiſer men perhaps, then any now alive, ſhould come now to be diſputed anew, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſs'd
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116879:8"/>and condemn'd perhaps. And ſeverall other opinions dogmatically obtruded upon the world, as the rules of the faith, good life, and obedience of all men, never heard of before.</p>
               <p>The two <hi>Houſes,</hi> and their well <hi>well-affected Party</hi> ſay; The King being wanting to his duty, in them is ſupplementally all Supreme power: and they being only Judges when he is wanting, may when they will inveſt themſelves with this power. For if to be wanting to them, is to be wanting to his duty, how many occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions may they take to make him wanting to his duty, when their paſſions ſhall put them upon demands not fit for his reaſon to grant them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Liburne,</hi> and his <hi>well-affected Party,</hi> [and thus there can be no Malignants, for every one is well affected to his own party] ſay, The Supreme power is in the <hi>Right Honourable</hi> the <hi>Houſe of Commons;</hi> which is a poſition, till this year of deliration never heard of; and yet perhaps, <hi>John Lilburne,</hi> and ſome of his, would ſeal this truth with their Blood, and call it Martyrdome to ſuffer for it. So that, call in Divines, Politicians, Lawyers, Logicians, and all the wit and underſtanding of the world to help us; I cannot ſee what end they can give to our diſtractions: For Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, Politicians, Lawyers, and Logicians are all divided: and the diſeaſe lies more in our will and affections, and about the heart, then in the braine. Men will not yield, becauſe they will not. We have more need of Charity to prepare &amp; ſoften, then of Councell to informe. For all reaſon being inflamed with paſſion, God muſt allay it with his good ſpirit of Grace and Truth, or we muſt ſtill remain the ſpectacle of madneſſe and fury to all the world, which <hi>He</hi> in mercy prevent, who is onely able to lay the ſtormes, and rebuke the wind of worldly commotions, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly this in <hi>England</hi> cauſing his ſpirit to move upon the hearts of all perſons now engaged in this preſent <hi>Treaty.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
